Back in lesson four, we learned that the
Android Runtime will kill apps with no visible activities,
in order to free resources needed by the foreground
app. But what if your app has tasks that
need to continue when the activity isn't visible, things
like downloading files, uploading photos, or playing music? Well,
there's an application component for that. Services. We've already
introduced Activities, Content Providers,
Broadcast Receivers and Intents. Services,
are the final piece to the Android app component
puzzle. You start services much like you do activities, by
passing in an intent to a Start Service call.
And you can stop services the same way, by calling
Stop Service and passing in the name of the
service you want to stop. Unlike activities, services have no
user interface and they run at a higher priority than
background activities. This means that an app with a running
service is less likely to be killed by the run
time, in order to free resources for the foreground activities.
In fact, by default, the system will attempt to restart
services that are terminated before they are stopped from within
the app. This is reflected in this simplified life cycle.
Compared to Activities, Services are designed to execute longer running
tasks that shouldn't be interrupted. Typically, you'll only need to
override the onStartCommad handler, which is where you begin the background
task you wish to execute. But notice that there are
no handlers for monitoring changes in state, to reflect the
app moving to the background. This is because the running
service itself sends a signal to the framework that the
containing app should be considered higher priority than other apps
in the background that don't have running services. In some
cases your service may performing a task, that while not
having UI, can't be interrupted without interfering with the user experience.
For example, playing music or helping with in car
navigation. In these cases, you can indicate that your
server should be considered to be running in the
foreground by calling startForeground. You'll notice that this call takes
in a notification. This will be displayed, and can't
be dismissed until the service has stopped, or you
call stopForeground. You'll learn more about notifications a little
later, with Dan. But for now, note that a foreground
service runs at the same priority as a foreground
activity. Making it nearly impossible for the run time
to kill in order to free resources. Now, you
may be thinking to yourself, I could save a lot
of trouble dealing with life cycles, just by creating
long running, or even foreground services. Well, I grew up
along the coast in Australia, so I learned young
that swimming against the current is exhausting and ultimately futile.
In this case, that means making it more difficult
for the system to manage resources, ultimately leading to a
worse user experience. Swim with the current. Use foreground
services only when and for as long as absolutely necessary,
and stop all services as quickly as possible. It's
also important to note that like activities and receivers, services
run on the main thread. So you'll need to
use a background thread or a think task to execute
the long running tasks you wish to do
within your service. To make life easier, you can
use the intent service class. Which implements the most
common best practice pattern, for using intents, which are
executed within a service. It creates a queue of
incoming intents, passed in when start service is called.
These are then, processed sequentially on a background thread,
within the onHandleIntent handler, within your intent service implementation.
When the queue is empty the service self terminates
until a new intent is received and the process begins
again. Services are a powerful tool and it's important
to understand how you can use them but in practice
there's often a framework alternative to rolling your own
service implementation. Whether that be an intent service for executing
background tasks or the sync adapter which you'll learn about
later in this lesson. Perfect for performing background data synchronization